主持人：请问这些数字和字母都是什么意思？
SuperBart：以下片段应该来自Doctor Who，我没看过，所以人物都是瞎写的
What do these numbers and letters mean?
爷爷：这应该是早期版本的程序，这些指令应该是机器代码吧
Well, it’s an early version. The instructions have to be punched in by machine code.
孙子：这个真没意思  爷爷：怎么会呢？
Oh how boring. Boring?
80年代的时候，我还很小，手边有VIC-20和C64
Back when I was a kid in the 80s with my Commodore VIC-20 and later C64,
那时我通过输入BASIC程序来学习编程
I had become a whiz at writing code in BASIC,
进而我能熟练地编写BASIC程序了
much of which I learned by typing in other BASIC programs
那些程序大多在编程书和杂志上
from books and magazines.
但当我搞到一份商业软件的时候
But as I began to acquire more commercial software,
我尝试列出程序源代码，可我只能看到
when I would attempt “list” the program, all I would see is a single line of
一行代码，上面只有SYS命令和一串数字
BASIC with an SYS command and some numbers.
我对其中原理一无所知，觉得这就是魔法:-P
I was mystified at how this worked. It was the equivalent of magic to me.
后来，我才知道这些程序是用机器语言编写的，简称ML
Later on, I was told that these programs were written in machine language,
or as we later called ML.
不光Commodore是这样，实际上，在大多数八位机上
This wasn’t just a Commodore thing. in fact, with most 8-bit systems,
百分之99的商业软件和游戏都是用机器语言写的
99% of commercial software and games were written in machine language.
这其中包括你喜欢的雅达利2600游戏，红白机游戏
This would include your favorite games on the Atari 2600,
the Nintendo Entertainment system, Apple II series, and so forth.
Apple II系列电脑上的游戏，当然还有很多
所以说，机器语言程序在当时是十分常见的，而不是个例
So, machine language was not the exception, in fact it was the norm.
本期视频，我想让大家稍微了解一下机器语言是啥
And in this episode, I hope to shed a little bit of light on what machine language actually is.
当然，我不会教你如何用机器语言编程
I’m not going to teach you how to code in machine language
因为这大概十个小时都教不完，而且十分枯燥:-(
as that would probably take like 10 hours and be pretty dry and boring.
但我还是希望大家能明白机器语言与
But I do hope to shed a little bit of light on on what machine language actually is
其他编程语言相比，有什么特点
as compared to other programming languages.
在我讲机器语言是啥之前，我想告诉大家它不是什么
And before I tell you what machine language is, I want to start be telling you what it isn’t.
我先从这个BASIC写的示例程序来说
I’ll start by showing you this little demonstration program I wrote in BASIC.
上一集我用它来测试，我觉得在这也一样
I actually used this in a previous episode as a benchmark, and I think it works well here too.
这个BASIC程序我尽力优化，以让其在1Mhz的电脑上运行
This is about as optimized as I can make it running here in BASIC on a 1 Mhz machine.
那时我们有一个为C64开发的程序，叫Blitz! Basic
注：程序翻译为 加速Basic程序
Now, back in the day we had this program for the Commodore 64 called Blitz! Basic.
应该也被叫做Austrospeed
And I think it was also known as Austrospeed.
在那时，我们对其能将BASIC编译为机器语言印象深刻
At the time, us common folk were under the impression
this would compile your BASIC program into machine language.
但实际上这不完全正确，别误会我，软件从来没有这么说过
But, that’s not actually true. Don’t get me wrong, the software never claimed to do this,
实际上它将源代码转换为了P-Code
rather it claimed to convert the code into something called P-Code.
实际上，P-Code也是一种解释型语言
And P-Code is just another interpreted language
只不过专门为运行速度而优化
but it happens to be much more optimized for speed.
如果你在编译程序后查看源代码，你只会看到Blitz!
If you try to list a program after compiling it, it will just say Blitz! Like this.
如图所示，显然源代码不能像BASIC一样可编辑
So the code is no longer editable as BASIC,
估计这也是为什么大家普遍认为它是机器语言
and I think that’s why the common belief was that it was machine language.
如你所见，与原版BASIC程序相比，Blitz!优化版要更快
But anyway, as you can see, if you compare the original program written in BASIC
to the one that was Blitzed, clearly the Blitz version runs much faster.
尽管还是赶不上机器语言的翻译速度，用Blitz!优化后
It’s still nowhere nearly as fast as machine language. With Blitz!,
基本上运行速度都要快2到8倍，看你用的是什么指令了
typical results can be anywhere from twice as fast to maybe 8 times as fast
depending on what instructions you are using.
所以，原理是什么呢？我给大家
So, how does this work? Well, for illustration,
举个例子，看一下这个示例程序，再看看Blitz!是怎么优化的
let’s take a look at this sample BASIC program, and let’s see how Blitz would optimize it.
首先，所有REM声明可以被省略
Well, for starters, any REM statements can be eliminated.
反正这是用来注释代码的
I mean, these are only here as comments in the code,
但是它占地儿啊，而且会略微减缓程序运行
but they take up space and slightly slow down execution.
既然代码已经无法编辑了，还不如删了呢:-)
And since the program can’t be edited anymore, might as well just delete it.
接下来，我们要看一下BASIC程序中各行代码
The next thing we can do is have a look at where all of the BASIC lines
在内存中的储存位置，并标出实际的内存地址
are actually stored in RAM and make note of their actual memory addresses.
然后我们看有行数的代码，像GOTO，GOSUB，还有NEXT
And then we can look at anything that points to a line number,
such as a GOTO, GOSUB, or even a NEXT statement,
然后搞明白它指向的内存地址
and figure out what it is they are pointing it.
一般来说，这些工作是在程序运行过程中执行的
Normally, this is done during execution,
而寻找代码行号，进而定位内存地址是相当耗费时间的
which takes time to look up the line number and find it’s memory address.
所以，为加快运行速度，你可以将行号换成对应的内存地址
So, to speed things up, you can actually
replace the line numbers with actual memory addresses,
那么，程序执行时就不需要找行号了
so no lookups will be done during execution.
当然，行号也不需要了，所以删掉他们就行了B-)
and, of course, we no longer need the line numbers,
so they can actually be removed from the code completely.
目前这里还有一些数可以优化，在BASIC代码里的这些数
OK, so here’s another thing that could use optimization.
Numbers like this stored in BASIC
实际上是纯字符，也可叫做字符串
are actually stored as raw text characters, a string if you will.
那么，像53280这样的数，实际上分别存于五个独立的字节中
So, a number like 53280 is actually stored as 5 separate bytes.
你可以用机器语言监视器打开程序，然后看到这种现象
You can actually see this if you look at
a BASIC program in a machine language monitor.
问题是，在程序执行过程中，数字字符必须转换成数字
Well, the trouble is, these numbers have to be
converted from strings to numbers during execution.
所以说，我们完全可以提前转换完，以节省程序运行时间
So again, we can go ahead and convert them now,
that way it saves time when the program is executing.
以上就是诸如Blitz这样的优化程序加速BASIC程序的方法了
And so, these are the types of enhancements that Blitz
or similar programs would do to speed up your BASIC programs,
但它们本质上还是BASIC程序
but they are still essentially BASIC programs,
它们依旧需要解释运行，根本不是机器语言
they are still being interpreted at time of execution, definitely not machine language.
但这本身并不是什么问题
But there isn’t necessarily anything wrong with this,
如果你是BASIC高手，这也是提升运行速度的方法之一
if you were good at programming in BASIC,
then this certainly gave you an option for some extra speed.
那么，到底什么是机器语言呢？
So, then, what is machine language?
这是种与处理器本身十分相关的语言
Well, this is the language that is native to your microprocessor.
处理器只会认识机器语言
This is the only language it knows.
你在电脑上运行的每一个程序，无论是在古董电脑上的
And every single piece of software you run on your computer,
whether it is a vintage computer, or a modern computer, has to be in machine language
还是在现代电脑上的，都是机器语言程序
要不然，电脑CPU不知道如何执行它
or your CPU won’t know how to execute it.
也就是说，你用其他语言编程，它们终会变成机器语言
Which means, if you ware writing code in some other language,
it will need to be converted into machine language.
而这有两种方法实现
There are two ways this can happen.
诸如 BASIC Java Python Ruby Perl 这样的语言
Languages like BASIC, Java, Python, Ruby, and Perl are all interpreted languages.
都是解释型语言，他们运行时都需要解释器
That means they need a separate piece of software called an interpreter,
亦可称运行时环境，它们运行时一行行读取代码
or sometimes called a run-time-environment, which will
look at your code one instruction at a time,
然后转换成CPU能执行的机器代码指令
and then convert that into machine language instructions for your CPU.
解释器必须与程序同时工作
This interpreter must always be present for your code to work.
在性能方面，解释型语言是比较慢的一类
Interpreted code also tends to be the slowest type of code in terms of performance,
但是它们的学习曲线更平缓
but also tends to have the easiest learning curve.
另一方面，诸如 C++, Pascal, C#, Cobol 和汇编语言
On the flip side, languages like C++, Pascal, C#, Cobol, and Assembly language
需要编译器编译，也就将代码永久翻译为机器语言
注：即编译型语言
are run through a compiler, which actually
transforms the code into machine language permanently.
只要编译完了，你不需要编译器就能运行程序了
Once this process is finished, you no longer need the compiler for the program to run,
当然，如果你需要更改程序的话，你还得用编译器:-(
although you might need it if you ever want to make changes to the code.
在性能方面，编译型语言较解释型语言更佳
These types of programs tend to have much better performance than interpreted languages,
但我之前说过，这个的学习曲线较为陡峭
but as mentioned before might have a bit higher learning curve.
那个，你们先不要去评论区说
Now, before you race to the comment section
我把Java和C#给分类错了
to tell me how I’m wrong about Java or C#,
我这个分类是一个相当笼统的分类
please understand that I’m making a generalization here
我也知道编程语言类型不是非此即彼的
and I do understand it isn’t quite this black and white.
主要在于，它们在运行中总归要变成机器语言
The point is, it has to be converted to machine language somewhere along the way.
那么，机器语言长什么样呢？
So, what does machine language look like?
基本上，它们就是堆数字
Well, at it’s core it’s just a bunch of numbers.
这个示例小程序能使C128显示边框闪烁
This small program is an example program that flashes the border on a Commodore 128.
第一个数字是CPU命令，亦称“指令”，俗称Op-Code
The first number here is a CPU command, or instruction, or Op-code, if you will.
这个指令可以将相应内存内容增1
注：EE=INC $addr16 EAC=A存储器单元内容增1
It commands the CPU to increment a number somewhere in memory.
接下来两个数是需要增1的内存地址
And the next two numbers are the memory address that needs to be incremented.
这个数字又是一个指令，是让CPU无条件跳转的
The next number is another instruction, this time telling the CPU to Jump,
或是跳转到另一块需要继续执行的内存
or goto some other place in memory to continue execution.
当然，指令接下来的两个数是需要跳转到的内存地址
And of course, the two numbers following that instruction
represent the memory address it’s going to jump to.
很早期的电脑实际上就是这么编程的
This is actually how early coding was done on computers
像Altair，前面板就是编程用开关
like the Altair with it’s panel of switches on the front panel,
或是KIM-1这样的老电脑
or computers like the KIM-1.
如果你还是很疑惑，不停地想：
Now, if that seems confusing to you and you’re thinking
“还有谁会用机器语言编写复杂的程序呢？”
“How on earth would anyone write complex programs in machine language?”
实际上，没人会，至少70年代之后就没有了
Well, the reality is, nobody did. Or at least not since the 1970s.
我现在给大家举个例子，当然不是吓唬你们啦
And I gave you this example, not to scare you away,
只是让大家明白机器语言和汇编语言的区别
but rather to help differentiate between machine language and assembly language.
平常我们都用，虽然它们之间关系紧密，但毕竟不是一个东西
These two terms are often used interchangeably,
and while they are closely related, they’re not exactly the same thing.
这有点像音乐和乐谱间的区别
It’s sort of like the difference between music, and musical score.
这俩之间有十分直接的关系，你听到的音符
They are very much related, and there is a one-to-one ratio
和乐谱上的音符能一一对应，但他们依然不是同一种东西
between the notes you hear and what is written on the paper.
But they aren’t exactly the same thing.
既然我说不明白，我还是给大家演示一下吧
And since I can’t think of a really good way to explain it,
I figure the best thing to do is just show you.
首先，我先用BASIC写一个能刷新显示边框的小程序
But first, I want to write a small program in BASIC. This program also flashes the border.
我觉得这个小程序可以说明一些问题
And I think this will help illustrate a few things.
它只是向显示边框寄存器依次写入0到225
It’s just going to count from 0 to 255
and then write that number to the screen border register.
然后不停重复以上步骤
And then we’re just going to repeat this indefinitely.
看上去程序执行得很快，边框更新速度快于屏幕显示速度
Now, this looks like it’s going pretty fast.
In fact, the border is changing faster than the screen is drawn,
这也是为什么边框出现了不止一个颜色
that’s why the border appears more than one color in places.
所以说，这就很快了吗？
So, that’s pretty fast right?
现在，我们用内置的机器语言监视器，用汇编语言重写程序
Well, now let’s write the same program in assembly language using the built in monitor.
我们先找到程序开始的内存地址，即十六进制的1300
So, we’re going to start our program at memory location 1300 hex.
我们现在需要往显示寄存器中增1
We’re going to increase the color value in the screen border.
这里的D020和BASIC里的53280是同一个数字
So, this D020 here is the exact same number as this 53280 we used in BASIC.
只不过一个是十六进制，一个是二进制
Just one is represented in decimal and the other one in hexadecimal.
现在看这三个数字，这是存储在内存中的机器语言数字代码
Also, see these 3 numbers here,
these are the actual machine code that is being stored in RAM.
右边的部分我们人类可以理解，我们称作汇编
The stuff to the right is just the human-readable form of that, which we call assembly.
这个机器语言命令是JMP，有点像BASIC里的GOTO
Anyway, our next instruction is JMP, which is similar to the GOTO statement in BASIC.
我们要跳回内存地址1300，也就是跳回开始，无限循环
And we’re going to jump to 1300, which takes us right back here in an infinite loop.
也就是说，这个程序比BASIC版的更小，更简单
So, this program is actually simpler and smaller than the BASIC code we wrote.
那么，我们退出监视器，回到BASIC环境，输入SYS启动程序
OK, so let’s exit the monitor back to BASIC and I’ll start the code by typing SYS,
SYS在Commodore BASIC中指机器语言程序
which in Commodore BASIC calls a machine language program,
地址是十进制的4864，即十六进制的1300
and the address is 4864, which is the same as 1300 hex.
好的，启动了。程序运行过快，显示单元每次只能
And so, there it is. So, this is actually running so fast that the border is
更新几个像素，看上去就更奇怪了
changing every few pixels of drawing the screen, making the thing look like this weird pattern.
现在，我要给大家写一个更简单的程序，先是BASIC版的
So, I’m going to give you one more example program here. Again, we’ll start in BASIC.
这个程序是将所有的225个字符全部显示出来
And what we’re going to do is count from 0 to 255 again,
and we’re going to display all 255 characters on the screen.
显示内存地址从1024开始
Screen memory starts at memory address 1024.
这样就行了，看看执行时长
And that should do it. And let’s see how long it takes to execute this code.
好的，大概三到四秒，这应该还行吧
OK, about 3 or 4 seconds. So, that’s not too bad, right?
现在我用机器语言监视器写机器语言版
OK, so now lets do the same code in the monitor.
程序就几行，我就写给大家看了
This is just a few lines so I’ll walk you through the code.
没都理解不要紧，大概能懂就行
Now, don’t worry if you don’t understand all of this, I think you’ll get the gist of it.
LDX命令能将寄存器X清零，即将X寄存器里的数值全部变成0
LDX means Load X with Zero. This just sets the value of the X register to zero.
TXA命令是将X寄存器的内容送入累加器
Next, TXA means Transfer X to the accumulator.
STA命令能将累加器内的内容变成400
Now STA means to store the accumulator at 400,
也就是显示内存地址1024的十六进制表示
which is the start of screen RAM in hexadecimal.
后面的',X'意思是在存储前累加寄存器X
The comma-X at the end means we’ll add the value of X to the address before the save.
INX命令能让寄存器X自增1
INX means to increase X by one.
然后我们要将寄存器X与0进行比较
Then we’re going to compare X to zero.
与零进行比较的原因是，这是台八位电脑
The reason we do zero is that if the value is 255
如果目前数值是225的话，再自增1的话，寄存器会归零
and you increase by one, it will wrap around to zero again since this is an 8-bit system.
比较后，如果不等于的话，CPU会继续运行
Now that we’ve compared, we’ll tell the CPU to branch if not equal back to 1302.
要是等于的话，就运行RTS命令，回到BASIC环境
If it is equal, then RTS will tell it to return back to BASIC.
好的，简单解释完了，现在执行
So, there we go, pretty simple. So, let’s execute the code.
运行得真快，我手指还没离开回车键就完事了
And as you can see, it is so fast that
it’s actually finished before I even lift my finger off of the return key.
我现在再运行一遍
So, I’ll show you that again, one more time.
现在你看到了汇编语言长啥样了，以下是《终结者》选段
So now that you’ve seen assembly language,
I’d love to show you this little scene from the Terminator.
这里显示的就是汇编语言，更准确说
What you are seeing here is assembly language, and more specifically
Apple II电脑上的6502机器语言，现在没几个人认得了
and more specifically 6502 assembly language from an Apple II.
Not many people today would recognize this.
所以说，为啥汇编版程序比BASIC版运行更快？
So, why is Assembly so much faster than BASIC?
我之前说过，BASIC是解释型语言
Well, as mentioned before, BASIC is interpreted.
每一条BASIC指令都要解释为好几百行机器语言指令
So for every BASIC command you see here,
hundreds of machine language instructions are happening to carry it out.
因而，机器语言版程序都要比任何BASIC程序快至少好几百倍
As such, a program in machine language will run
at least a hundred times faster than anything you can write in BASIC.
现在我得说明一下，机器语言不止一种
Now, it is at this point I think I should stop and mention to you
that there is more than one kind of machine language.
如果用C语言，或是Python语言写程序的话，你可以
Now, when you write code in like C or Python, there’s
在不同架构CPU的电脑上运行它
a good chance that code is going to run on any computer with any CPU.
但机器语言编程十分依赖你电脑上的CPU
But, machine language is very dependent on the CPU that you are coding for.
比如说，在6502上写的汇编程序无法在Z80上运行
So, code written on a 6502, for example, will not run on a Z80.
这两个CPU的机器语言不相同
They are very different languages.
但这期视频，我还是用6502机器语言举例，因为这个还算简单
But for the purposes of this video, I’m going to stick with the 6502
because I think it’s one of the simplest to understand.
6502 CPU有151个CPU指令，但大多数在实践中用不到
The 6502 CPU has 151 op-codes. But, it’s really not that many in practice.
实际上，记下56个指令就够用了
In fact, you only need to remember 56 instructions.
比如说，如果你要将数值加载至寄存器，你可以用LDA指令
For example, if you are using the command LDA,
which means to load a number into the accumulator.
你可以直接加载一个数，诸如42
You can tell it to load a specific number like 42,
或者你可以像这样，加载一个内存地址
or you can tell it to load the number from a specific memory address like this.
你再看左边，里面的CPU指令是不同的
As you can see, looking over to the left here, the actual CPU op-codes are different,
但是我们没必要搞明白这些东西
but as a human, you don’t really need to know the difference
汇编器能够找到对应的CPU指令
as your assembler will take care of figuring out which op-code to use.
目前，我都是在机器语言监视器中编写程序
Now, what I shown so far has been using a machine language monitor,
它可以查看并修改机器语言指令
which allows you to look at and modify machine code.
但你肯定不想在这里写一些很多很多行的程序
But you wouldn’t want to really write any sort of code in this
that was longer than just a few lines.
因为你要为写很多子程序而记忆很多内存地址
Because you’d have to remember a ton of memory addresses for every sub-routine.
而且基本不能插入代码，你只能将代码给覆盖了
But the worst part is there is no easy way to insert a line of code.
Generally you can only overwrite a line.
相比之下，汇编器就很好用了
That’s where using a compiler comes in handy.
以下是我最近编写的游戏的代码片段
So, here’s some of my source code for my recent game, Attack of the PETSCII Robots.
如你所见，这些代码都是用文本编辑器写的
As you can see, this is written in a text editor,
看上去更好用了，每个子程序都有好理解的内存地址名
and looks far more friendly, with subroutines that have friendly names
诸如 Search Object 和 Display Player Sprite
寻找对象
显示玩家图像
like “search object” or “display player sprite.”
所以汇编器更好用嘛，那汇编器是怎么工作的呢？
And this is where an assembler makes life so much easier. So, how does this work?
这里我拿记事本写了一个小程序
Well, here’s a very short little example program written in a notepad.
在编译后，我将用机器语言监视器看看编译后成了啥样
Now, after compiling the program I’m going to open it up
in the machine language monitor and see what it looks like.
首先，汇编中所有的指令都被照搬了
So, the first thing I want to mention is that the actual instructions are preserved one to one.
机器语言和汇编在这方面没有任何区别
There’s absolutely no difference here.
但是，内存地址名都变成了内存地址，比如‘screen RAM’
屏幕显示内存
However, our friendly label such as “screen RAM”
has been converted to the actual memory address for us.
还有，我用来循环用的命令也编译成相应内存地址了
Likewise, the labels I used for the loop,
have also been converted into the actual memory address,
这个地址正好就是我标注的循环开始地址
which, of course, corresponds to the exact place in the code where it is supposed to point to.
当然，如果你想直接看机器代码本身的话
And, of course, if you just wanted to see the resulting machine code itself,
你也可以直接看这个
you can look at that as well.
希望我刚才能说明白机器语言和汇编语言的区别
And so I hope this better explains the difference between this,
which is machine code or machine language, and this, which is assembly language.
它们就是一个东西的两个面目罢了
They are really just two different ways of looking at the same thing.
在以前，有些程序员确实需要用机器语言编程
And while back in the early days, some coders did have to write software in machine language,
大量使用汇编器，使代码更加可读
the vast majority used an assembler to write code that is more human-readable.
那么，你可能会有疑问了，为什么汇编用的数字都是十六进制？
So, one thing you might be wondering about is
why everything in assembly language uses hexadecimal?
在此，我要解释一下十六进制是啥
So, I want to explain a few things about it. For those that don’t know,
十六进制是十六进一，而不是十进一
it is a numbering system that is based on 16 digits instead of 10,
另外还多了A,B,C,D,E.F六个字符
and it just adds A,B,C,D,E, and F for the extra 6 digits.
为什么用它很方便呢？因为我们处理二进制数字时
The reason this is handy is because when dealing with byte sized numbers,
一个十六进制数可以表示四个比特，行话叫nybble
半字节
a single hex digit can represent 4 bits of your byte,
which is actually called a nybble by the way.
因此，十六进制的9A就比十进制的154好记多了
So, 9A is much easier to read than the decimal form of 154.
还有一个好处是在写汇编语言时，频繁查看内存地址
A possibly better example would be looking at memory addresses,
which is something you do a lot in assembly language.
对于CPU来说，64K的内存寻址是在十进制的0到65535之间
In decimal, the 64K memory range of a CPU would be represented from 0 to 65535.
但是，用十六进制表示的话，是0到FFFF
But, in hex it is a much cleaner 0 to FFFF.
而这在用比特形式看内存地址时，就十分管用了
注：一个比特等于八位二进制数字
But where things get really interesting is when looking at a memory address in terms of bytes.
这是同一个内存地址，分别用十六进制和十进制表示
So here’s the same address in Hex and Decimal.
这个地址是C64中表示显示边框颜色的地址
You might recognize this as the border color address on a Commodore 64,
你可以用POKE命令来更改边框颜色
which you can use a POKE statement to change the border color.
在汇编中，这个地址正好用两个比特表示
Well, in assembly language this address has to be represented by exactly two bytes.
用十六进制表示的话，正好是D0和20，挺好理解
And in hexadecimal, those two bytes are D0, and 20. Which, makes total sense.
1101 0000
0010 0000
但用十进制的话，这两个比特就成了208和32，完全理解不能
But in decimal, those two bytes are 208 and 32. Which doesn’t appear to make any sense at all.
实际上，这么写是正确的，不过得算一下
In fact, you have to do some math to actually see that this is right.
你先算208*256=53248，然后将低位的32加上，得到53280
注：十六进制中，“个位”代表1，“十位”代表16，“百位”代表16*16=256
You’ll need to multiply 208 by 256, which gives you 53248,
and then add in your 32 from the lower byte and then you get your final number.
如你所见，程序员处理十六进制的话，会更加顺手
So, as you can see, programers find it much easier
just to deal with things like this in hexadecimal.
看看，连他们都在 Logopolis 上使用二进制
And of course, if they use hexadecimal on Logopolis,
所以十六进制真是电脑之友啊:-)
that’s all the proof you need that it’s the best system for computers!
孙子:......23，等会，您刚才是说E9吗？这写的是E7！
9A, E7, E9, sorry, E9, 23, wait wait, did you say say E9? Look it says E7 there!
爷爷：你说的没错！
You’re right!
关于十六进制，我最后再说一下它应该怎么写
One last thing about hexadecimal I wanted to mention is how it is represented.
在6502汇编语言，PASCAL，Delphi和Forth语言中
I’ve been showing it with a dollar sign in front of it like this, which is
我们要在十六进制数前加上'$'符号
the normal way to identify it in 6502 assembly language, PASCAL, Delphi, and Forth.
而对于8088汇编，C++，C#，Java，Python等语言来说
But, another way to represent it is to put a zero X in front of it like this,
我们要在十六进制数前加上'0x'符号
which is common in 8088 assembly language, C++, C#, Java, Python, and many others.
这些数本质相同，只是编译器识别十六进制的标记不同罢了
The numbers work exactly the same,
it’s just a different way of designating it as hex in the compiler.
汇编语言及其相关知识本身是不难的
Assembly language in and of itself is not that difficult.
在某些方面，用汇编编程会更简单，比如图形编程
In fact, there are certain things that are actually
easier to do in assembly language such as graphics programming.
但是有利必有弊，某些领域不适合用汇编编程
But there are some tradeoffs. And there are certain things that are kind of a pain.
比如字符串相关程序，用汇编编程的话，会很麻烦:-P
For example, working with strings. That’s a nightmare to work with in assembly language.
然而，我认为汇编语言的难点的根源在于
However, I think the thing that often makes assembly language more difficult
你必须了解你所编程的硬件的工作原理
is the fact that you have to know how the hardware works that you’re coding for.
假设在 6502 处理器的电脑上，你用汇编语言编程
With assembly language, and in the example of the 6502 processor,
你得用56个汇编命令，本质上，这些命令的作用
you have your 56 instructions, and all of these more or less
就是在内存中移动数字
have to do with moving numbers around in memory.
那么，像更改画面或是发出音乐这些事，是怎么做到的呢？
So, how do you actually do things like
modify things on the screen or make music, for example?
对于CPU，电脑上每个芯片都被看作是内存之类的东西
Well, every chip in the computer presents itself as memory of some sort to the CPU.
比如C64上的显示芯片，在内存中就被看作是
So, in the C64 for example, the video chip presents itself as
47个内存地址，从$D000到$D02E
47 different memory addresses starting from $D000 to $D02E.
既然它不是内存，我们姑且称其为寄存器
When it is not memory, we tend to call them registers.
不过对于CPU来说，这俩东西没什么不同
But from the perspective of the CPU, it can’t tell the difference.
那么，如果我们向显示边框寄存器写入数值的话
So, when we write a number to the border color register, for example,
CPU认为是向某块内存写入数值
the CPU just thinks it is just updating a number in memory,
但实际上，数值被写入显示芯片里的某个寄存器了
but what is really happening it’s updating a register in the video chip.
所以，对于程序员来说，你必须熟悉电脑芯片里的
So, as a programmer, you’d have to make yourself familiar with
每一个寄存器，及其工作原理
all of the registers in every chip on the computer and how they work.
当然，如果将某个平台的汇编程序移植到另一个平台
And of course, when you move from one computer, like the C64
诸如将C64的程序移植到Apple II
over to another computer such as the Apple II,
就算这两台电脑用的是一样的CPU
even though they use the same processor,
其他的东西也完全不同啊
everything else is completely different.
这就是移植游戏非常难的原因
That’s why it can be incredibly difficult to port a game from one machine to another.
我觉得这就是为什么我写了两个游戏
I think that’s why people are often confused when they see that I’ve written these games
like Planet X3, or Attack of the Petscii Robots,
而不移植到某些人常用平台的
and they want me to make a version for their favorite computer.
就算是两种电脑的CPU相同，移植起来也不容易
Now even going between systems that share the same CPU, it’s still a pretty big undertaking.
实际上，确实有一个Apple II的兴趣小组正在将
In fact, there’s a small team of Apple II guys that have been working to
这个游戏移植到Apple II
convert Petscii Robots over to the Apple II
如你所见，大多数功能都实现了
and as you can see, it is mostly working now.
当然，Apple II和Commodore电脑用的是同一个CPU
Keep in mind the Apple II has the same CPU as Commodore systems,
所以，这俩版程序里的很多代码可以共用
so a huge amount of the code is re-usable between these systems.
但你还是得重写所有的音频，视频引擎，这个十分麻烦
But it’s still a massive undertaking to re-write all of the audio and video sub-routines.
如果有人想让我将游戏移植到使用不同CPU的平台
But then when people suggest that
I make a version of my game for system that uses a different CPU,
诸如移植到Amiga，ZX Spectrum之类的平台
for example asking me to make an Amiga or ZX spectrum version or something like that,
这基本上就是重写程序了
at that point it becomes a complete rewrite.
所以说，这工作可不容易，如果我花一年来写游戏的话
So, it’s no small task. I mean, if it took me a year to write the game in the first place,
那我就得再花一年来重写这个游戏
then it would take me another year to basically write the whole game again from scratch.
我觉得现在人们特别喜欢现代语言的原因是
And I think this is where a lot of people are
spoiled by modern programming languages because
如果你用C或是Python编程的话，基本上这个程序
if you write something in C or Python, fundamentally
you can expect that same code is probably
可以在多种CPU平台上，或是不同的内存平台上运行
going to run across multiple different CPUs on multiple different systems,
on multiple different memory configurations.
基本上编程是单向的，你可以将高级语言编译成机器语言
Machine language basically goes one direction.
You can compile a program from a higher level language into machine language.
如果你乐意的话，你也可直接用机器语言编程
Or you can write in machine language to begin with, if you want.
但是反过来就不行了:-(
注：前一种叫反编译，后面说的是扒谱
But you can’t go back the other direction.
相当于按照乐谱演奏交响曲，但你很难将交响曲变成乐谱
Much like you can convert notes on a sheet of music into a symphony.
It’s much more difficult to convert the symphony back into notes.
或者说炒鸡蛋，你可以将鸡蛋变成炒鸡蛋
Another example would be scrambling an egg. It’s easy to do it one direction,
但变回去就不可能了
but unscrambling is a different story.
如今，汇编编程的艺术很少被人提及
Today, Assembly language is more or less a lost art.
编译器可以将高级语言编译成性能很好的机器语言代码
Modern compilers are pretty good at creating
optimized machine code from higher level languages.
现在计算机性能太强了，以至于编译中的性能损失可以忽略了
And computers are also just so darned fast that
any speed loss you might have is pretty much negligible these days.
甚至很多操作系统，比如Linux内核，是用C编写的
I mean, even operating systems like the Linux kernel are written in C.
所以说，现在用汇编语言编程并没有什么优势
So, assembly language today doesn’t really offer that much benefit for the modern coder.
但你要在上世纪七八十年代的电脑上写游戏的话
But if you want to write games for computers that were madden the 1970s or 80s,
学习机器语言是十分必要的
learning machine language is pretty much a must.
如果你学的话，最后你会懂得很多计算机运行的原理
And if you do learn it, you’ll probably wind up finding out
a whole lot more information about how computers actually work.
好了，还有一件事，如果你看了我的新工作室
OK, one last thing I want to mention, if you’re looking around at the new studio
觉得这个比以前的要单调的话
and you’re thinking "well gee, David,
this studio looks pretty boring compared to your old one!"
实际上，这个工作室还没完工
Well, it’s actually not done yet.
但是以前的工作室我给拆了，别的地方也不行
The problem is the old studio has already been dismantled so I didn’t have anywhere to film,
所以我只能在这拍了，不过几周内我尽量
so it had to be done in here. But yeah, I’m going to do a whole other follow up
拍一个新工作室装修视频
video in another couple of weeks here hopefully,
给大家看看新工作室里面装修完是啥样，希望有所不同
showing the finishing up of the interior of the studio
and it will look... hopefully quite a bit different.
希望大家关注哦，最后，感谢大家观看:-)
So anyway, stay tuned for that, and as always thanks for watching!
时间轴+翻译：SuperBart
校对:
原作者The 8-Bit Guy上传于2021-2-14
注意：本字幕只能由Youtube上The 8-Bit Guy频道的官方授权方发布，其他人不得商用!